Slim Ouertani June-81, Tunisian

ouertani@gmail.com • (00966)-(0)-583012381 • Riyadh (Saudi Arabia) linkedin.com/in/ouertani • ouertani.github.io • jroller.com/ouertani • twitter.com/ouertani

Architect, InfoQ Fr Editor Founder & Organiser of Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup Big Data Science, Cloud & SOA Certified Trainer Togaf, Archimate, SABSA, PMP, Spring, Java, Cmmi, ITIL, Mongo, Scala

Summary

Slim Ouertani is solution architect, InfoQ-Fr editor, Big Data Science, Cloud and SOA Certified trainer , founder and organizer of Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup. After his engineer's degree in computer science, Slim spent over than 10 years in multinational companies such as Orange, Sagem and STMicroelectronics as architect, international agile coach and Head of IT development department. His main role was to build, design and collaborate in the development of enterprise solutions.

Slim regularly contributes to InfoQ-FR community where he is the author of many articles and news. you to follow him on twitter @ouertani.

He's broad certified as in addition to his SOA, Cloud and Big Data Science certifications: Trainer, Architect & Engineer, Slim holds multiple certifications including Togaf 9, Archimate 2, SABSA, PMP, ITIL, CMMi, Mongo, Spring, JAVA, SCALA and reactive programming...

Trained as an architect, Slim specializes in enterprise Java development, functional programming focusing on highly scalable applications and now expanding his experience to cloud computing.

Slim enjoys open source contribution and invite

Experience

Al-Elm Information Security

Solution Architect

RIYADH, SAUDI ARABIA

06-2014 - present

- Member/Founder of ELM Development Architecture Center of Excellence.
- EPG committee member, responsible of the architecture models, oversee the process architecture, approve it and ensuring the process improvement.
- Architecting and Designing enterprise solutions using diverse technology stack
 Work with peers to conduct Solution Architecture Reviews for a broad set of projects

- Review and provide input into functional & non-functional requirements
 Provide consulting and conduct reviews through the development lifecycle
 Defining the Architecture and guiding the use of various tools, technologies and techniques in the realization of that Architecture
- Create and maintain a set of standard practices, patterns and anti-patterns and ensure the appropriate usage of that.

Sofrecom (Orange FT Group)

Tunis, Tunisia 03-2013 - 06-2014

Software Architect, International Agile Coach

- Manage and direct virtual distributed teams
- Make or Buy Analysis
- Establish regular meetings to review technical designs and provide mentoring and guidance
- Mentor development teams on different architecture and design paradigms or practices
- Maintain a knowledge base of emerging technologies and products
- Scrum Master, Enterprise Architect, Apache Camel, Spring
 CXF, Spring Batch, Atomikos, ActiveMq, Jonas, hibernate

Zenika

Paris, FRANCE

12-2012 - 03-2013

JEE Architect

• Client: Bouygues Telecom

- Project: Home Automation (2 months)
- BBox embedded automation solution communicating with centralized system

 - Embedded: OSGI, REST server/client, Raspberry pi- Server: Fuse ESB, CXF, Camel, Spring, Jax-Rs, Osgi, Maven
- Client: SwissPost
- Project: Image Plus (2 months)
- Online outsourcing solution for picture processing.
 - Scrum, Kanban, Jenkies, Git, Cloudbees, Maven

- MVP, Spring 3.1, GWT 2.5, JPA 2

Orange Tunis, Tunisia

Head of Development and Tools Manager

01-2010 - 11-2012

- JEE 6, MDB, JPA, Scala, Wicket, Play, J2ME, Spring ROO, WS, Glassfish, Talend, Birt
- Development and implementation of a web service platform :

JEE 6, SCALA, EJB 3.1, JAX-WS, Oracle, JPA

- JEE 6, SCALA, EJB 3.1, JAX-WS, Olacle, JFA
 IN/AIR, BSCS/CMS/Data Charging/CRM/IVR/USSD
 Development of the "after sales service" solution: Play 1.2.x, groovy, jquery
 Launch of BI project: Talend, Birt, Oracle
 Bulk SMS: Wicket, JEE 6, JPA, Postgres
 Unbarring SMS: J2ME, JAX-WS, MDB, JPA
 Different applications: intersystems and synchronization platforms, web an

- Different applications: inter systems and synchronization platforms, web application...

Sagem Software & Technologies

Tunis, Tunisia

Solution Architect

06-2009 - 01-2010

- · Architecture design and integration of a communication server and administration of remote
 - JEE, JMS, Spring, GWT, AndroMda, Hibernate, SMS – JEE, JMS, Spring, C. – Jboss, ActiveMq, MDA

03-2008 - 06-2009**Solution Architect**

- Modular OSGi Server architecture under Linux platform responsible for controlling and interacting with electricity counters in order to retrieve statistics and have data storing/manipulation via different technologies and frameworks
 - OSGI, SCA, Spring DM, JAX-WS, JPA, GPRS, GSM/DATA, SMS, SNMP4j, Hessian, Ftp, Equinox, JETTY, POSTGRESQL
 - DISTRIBUTED COMPUTING, Cryptography

Solution Architect & Team Leader

12-2007 - 03-2008

- Designing an SOA architecture and implementation of an Intranet service for human resources using liferay portal.
 - JEE5, EJB3, JAX-WS, JSF, PORTLET, JPA, SOA
- GLASSFISH V2, TOMCAT6, LIFERAY 4.4, POSTGRESQL

STMicroelectronics Tunis, Tunisia

• Implementing Intranet tools used for monitoring the evolution of validation campaigns.

02-2006 - 12-2007Coordinator

J2EE, JSF, Hibernate/JPA, JAXB/JAXP, Design PatternTOMCAT 5.5, POSTGRESQL

12-2005 - 02-2006 Developer

- Validating processors and compilers under different platforms.
 - Linux, Solaris, Cygwin, Mingwin, Perl, Shell

GL TRADE Tunis, Tunisia

Developer & designer

08-2005-12-2005

 GL TACTICS: A trader module enhancing the efficiency of the negotiating teams giving them the possibility to customize the implementation strategies and accelerate the decision process.

- C++, Design Pattern

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of work experiences along with recommendations.

Certificate

SABSA Foundation 2 - Security Service Management, Arcitura Score 88%, 11-2016 SABSA Foundation 1 - Security Strategy Planning, Arcitura Score 90%, 11-2016 Big Data Science Trainer, Arcitura 09-2016 Big Data Science Engineer, Arcitura WITH HONORS, 08-2016 Big Data Professional, Arcitura With Honors, 05-2016 Archimate Certified, Open Group Score 82%, 02-2016 Archimate Foundation, Open Group Score 97%, 02-2016 Cloud Trainer, Arcitura 10-2015 Cloud Architect, Arcitura WITH HONORS, 10-2015 Cloud Professional, Arcitura WITH HONORS, 09-2015

Togaf Certified, Open Group	Score 90%, 06-2015
ITIL Foundation, Exin	Score 95%, 06-2015
Togaf Foundation, Open Group	Score 95%, 04-2015
Project Management Professional, PMI	03-2015
SOA Trainer, Arcitura	01-2015
SOA Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 12-2014
SOA Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 11-2014
Introduction to Cmmi for development, Cmmi Institute	09-2014
Entrepreneurship for all, EFFECTUATION, EMLYON	Score 75,8%, 01-2014
Principles of Reactive Programming, Coursera	Score 97.5%, 01-2014
MongoDB for DBAs, MongoDB	Score 94%, 11-2013
MongoDb for java, MongoDb	Score 95%, 10-2013
Spring Framework 3, Pivotal	Score 94%, 02-2013
Java 6 Programmer Certified Professional, Oracle	Score 100%, 08-2012
Team Performance, STMicroelectronics	04-2007
English, British Council	4B, 02-2007
GL Certified Professional, GL TRADE	09-2005

Education

National School of Computer ScienceENSI Graduation Project in Computer Engineering	Tunis,Tunisia 2005
National School of Computer Science ENSI Engineer Degree in Computer Science	Tunis, Tunisia 2002 – 2005
Tunis Preparatory Institute for Engineering StudiesIPEIT Preparatory Courses (Math Sup, Math Spe)	Tunis, Tunisia 2000 – 2002
Hannibal (Pre-university Secondary Education)	Ariana, Tunisia 1994 – 2000

Other Activities

InfoQ Fr Editor

http://www.infoq.com/fr/author/Slim-Ouertani

BLOGGGING

http://java.dzone.com/users/slim.ouertani http://ouertani.github.io

http://www.jroller.com/ouertani

http://twitter.com/ouertani

MAGAZINE

From Microservices to SOA - 20.07.2015 Service Technology Magazine - Issue XCI http://servicetechmag.com/I91/0715-1

OPEN SOURCE

https://github.com/ouertani http://www.reactive-streams.org

Founder & Organizer

Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup

http://www.meetup.com/Riyadh-IT-Architecture

INTERVIEW

Paremus, SCA with OSGI, David Savage

http://www.prosyst.com/

07.02.2009

http://goo.gl/H5yJzY

STAMPLE

https://stample.co Scala, Akka, Play

ElasticSearch, MongoDb, Amazon S3, GreenCloud

Arcitura Authorized Training Partner

http://www.arcitura.com/ Big Data Science, Cloud & SOA

Computer Skills

Architecture Microservices, Reactive, N-tiers, SOA, SCA, Actor <u>EA</u> Togaf, Archimate, Sparx Functional programming, EA, UML, Design Pattern, MVC, MDA, OO, MVP Design Architecture Microservices, Reactive, N-tiers, SOA, SCA, Actor Cloud CloudBees, Heroku, App Engine, Amazon S3, GreenCloud Agile Scrum, Kanban CollaborationTrello, Slack, Github, Codex, Wiki, Sharepoint, IceScrum, Bugzilla **Training** Project Management Professional, PMP 11.2014 OSGi design pattern: White board & Extender 08.2009 By: Slim Ouertani SCA architecture with Newton 01.2009 By: David Savage & Mike Francis OSGi, architecture and environment 05.2008 By: Roman Roelofsen **Publications** Pour le fun: for-comprehension à la sauce Java 8 23.07.2015 Vrais ou Faux Jumeaux? 25.11.2014 Curryfication Java: methods & fonctions 29.07.2014 Des Lenses en Java? 30.06.2014 Barboter dans le compilateur Java 02.06.2014 Mon Trampoline avec Java 8 18.04.2014 Démystifier les iteratees avec Java 01.11.2013 Le Trio: Akka, Spring et Scala 16.10.2013 Rest with Scala and Vert.x 18.02.2013 Fun with Scala and Vert.x 11.02.2013 Getting Started with Play 2.1, Scala 2.10 and Slick 0.11.1 01.11.2012 Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of publications since 2008. News Publication de la Nouvelle Spécification d'ArchiMate 3.0 22.06.2016 Java EE et les Anges Gardiens 11.05.2016 Microservice antipatterns à Qcon London 2016 14.04.2016 MongoDB: la magie des Reactive-Streams avec les Capped Collections 21.05.2015 Publication de l'API Reactive Streams 1.0

Docker, le dernier clou dans le cercueil des serveurs d'applications Java?

Languages

Arabic, French English

WRITTEN & SPOKEN

07.05.2015

19.03.2015